¬ Do not remove or translate this line


{Teutoburg00}
This is the year 9 AD.

{Teutoburg01}
The place: Germania, beyond the Empire’s border. 

{Teutoburg02}
This is the army of Quinctilius Varus, sent north by Augustus to pacify the Germans. 

{Teutoburg03}
Guided by a trusted local chieftain, Arminius, the Legion is heading back to winter camp. But life on the frontier can be treacherous, brutal and short. 

{Teutoburg04}
Thanks to Arminius, the Romans are marching into danger. Hidden in the forest there’s an army of savage German warriors, fired up and thirsty for Roman blood. 

{Teutoburg05}
As the danger becomes obvious, Varus gallops to the head of the column. 

{Teutoburg06}
He has to get his men back to the fort before sunset. Once darkness falls, the Germans will be able to kill them at will. 

{Teutoburg07}
This is a chance for Varus to prove that he has the right stuff. That he is a noble Roman, and a noble Roman general at that. 

{Teutoburg08}
If he isn’t, he’ll be a noble Roman corpse by sunset. And no one will get home. 

{Teutoburg09}
The camp is in sight. 

{Teutoburg10}
One last push by the Romans should see them home. But without enough survivors, this will be a black day for Rome – and a massive victory for the barbarians! 

{Trebia01}
The river Trebia. 218 BC

{Trebia02}
Having sworn an oath at his father’s deathbed … 

{Trebia03}
… the young Hannibal Barca, general of the mighty Carthaginians, sets out to destroy the Romans.

{Trebia04}
Having lost many men marching across the freezing Alps, Hannibal gathers the survivors and prepares to face the might of Rome.

{Trebia05}
His forces are no match for the Roman legions. Hannibal must use the element of surprise if he is to have a chance.

{Trebia06}
He hides his finest cavalry in the forests.

{Trebia07}
And then sends his Numidian mercenary cavalry across the river to lure the Romans into the trap.

{Trebia08}
The Romans take the bait and chase the Numidians back across the freezing river.

{Trebia09}
And the scene is set for Hannibal to stage his ambush.

{Trebia10}
Timing is crucial. 

{Trebia11}
If his cavalry charge too soon, they’ll be isolated and cut down by the Roman infantry.

{Trebia12}
If they charge too late, the Carthaginian front line will buckle before the Roman advance.

{Trebia13}
Hannibal also knows that he must use his elephants to create fear and terror.

{Trebia14}
Failure to use these two key units to maximum effect will spell disaster for Hannibal’s campaign against Rome.

{Pharsalus00}
By 48 BC the long struggle between Julius Caesar and Pompey was coming to an end. One or the other would be the dictator of Rome. The old Republic would be no more, swept aside by a time when one strong man would rule all.

{Pharsalus01}
The Battle of Pharsalus was to be a turning point. 

{Pharsalus02}
Earlier in the year the two had met at Dyrrhachium in Greece. Pompey had won and Caesar had retreated. 

{Pharsalus03}
Rather than go back to Rome and rally support in the Senate, Pompey decided to finish Caesar, to hunt him down and destroy him. If Caesar was left alone, what mischief would he get up to? 

{Pharsalus04}
This was to be a fight to the death. 

{Pharsalus05}
For his part, Caesar was happy to finish the business too. He had fallen back towards his armies’ supplies and reinforcements. If Pompey wanted a fight, he could have one!

{Pharsalus06}
After two month of marching and countermarching the two sides met. Pompey chose a hill near the town of Pharsalus and made his stand. 

{Pharsalus07}
Caesar ordered his battle lines to advance. 

{Pharsalus08}
The rest, as they say, is history…

{Spartacus01}
Mount Vesuvius. 72 BC.

{Spartacus02}
This is the army of Spartacus, a force causing fear throughout Italy.

{Spartacus03}
Thousands of the slaves have escaped from their Roman masters, and now fill the ranks of a gladiator-led army on the slopes of Mount Vesuvius.

{Spartacus04}
Spartacus has already crushed two Roman Legions.

{Spartacus05}
The wealthy Roman Senators have panicked. Marcus Marcus Lucinius Crassus, the most ambitious man in Rome, now has command. His mission: destroy Spartacus and all his followers.

{Spartacus06}
Pompey the Great has been recalled from Spain and his 8 Legions are only two days’ march from Vesuvius.

{Spartacus07}
Spartacus knows that he must break Crassus before Pompey arrives.

{Spartacus08}
Crassus has set up camp at the foot of the volcano. His legions are ready.

{Spartacus09}
Spartacus knows that his slave army has little chance in an open battle. He has a plan to sneak into camp with his finest warriors and kill Crassus.

{Spartacus10}
If Crassus dies, Spartacus and his army will be able to slip away in the confusion. The rebellion will continue! Freedom and escape from Rome will still be possible!

{Carrhae01}
Carrhae, 55 BC.

{Carrhae02}
The army of Marcus Lucinius Crassus marches deep into Parthia. 

{Carrhae03}
Crassus is in the East looking for glory and riches. He needs both in the struggle for ultimate power back in Rome.

{Carrhae04}
For weeks he has marched after the Parthian army. They are drawing him deep into their own lands.

{Carrhae05}
Now the Romans think that the Parthians won’t fight, and the Roman cavalry are too far ahead of the main column.

{Carrhae06}
They’ve ridden straight into a Parthian trap.

{Carrhae07}
Heavy cataphracts close in -

{Carrhae08}
- And easily massacre the outnumbered Roman cavalry.

{Carrhae09}
Now the Parthian horse archers are free to harass the Roman infantry.

{Carrhae10}
Crassus orders his legions to form the ‘testudo’ as protection against arrow fire - 

{Carrhae11}
This leaves them vulnerable in hand to hand combat - 

{Carrhae12}
- and the Cataphracts are on their way.

{Carrhae13}
Only the few remaining Roman cavalry will have any chance of routing the Parthian horse archers!

{Cynocephalae01}
Thessaly, Northern Greece

{Cynocephalae02}
This is the army of Titus Flaminius, camped below the Cynoscephalae ridge.

{Cynocephalae03}
It is morning, and Flaminius has sent a scout party up onto the ridge to survey the terrain.

{Cynocephalae04}
Two days have passed since the Macedonians were first sighted at Pherae to the South. There, Flaminius defeated Philip in a cavalry skirmish. 

{Cynocephalae05}
Flaminius suspects that the enemy are close by.

{Cynocephalae06}
How right he will turn out to be!

{Cynocephalae07}
Philip has formed his phalanx spearmen into a line across the top of the ridge.

{Cynocephalae08}
It's going to be a difficult battle - phalanx spearmen are tough to beat in a frontal assault, especially going uphill.

{Cynocephalae09}
However, not all of Philip's left flank is in position. A decisive strike here could be a chance to seize the initiative.

{Cynocephalae10}
To arms, then! To the task at hand! May the strength of the Eagle carry the day!

{Mancetter00}
Winter. 60 AD. 

{Mancetter01}
This is the new northern province of Britannia, a strange land of violent, ungrateful natives and dark magic. 

{Mancetter02}
Roman law is finally being imposed here. 

{Mancetter03}
The Roman Governor, Suetonius Paulinus, is busy suppressing the druids, a vicious religious cult from Mona, an island off the west coast. It’s a dirty job, but one that needs doing. 

{Mancetter04}
Meanwhile, the Queen of the Iceni has seen her husband die. Then the Romans take her lands, rape her daughters and beat her to within an inch of her life. 

{Mancetter05}
Roman law is being imposed, but for the benefits of Romans, not the natives.  

{Mancetter06}
This particular native Queen has other ideas. 

{Mancetter07}
Queen Boudicca wants revenge. She wants Roman blood spilled until the rivers run red. 

{Mancetter08}
Two tribes – the Iceni and the Trinobantes – have risen in rebellion. 

{Mancetter09}
Three Roman settlements have been put to the sword and burned. 

{Mancetter10}
There is no going back.

{Mancetter11}
As Paulinus marches south to meet the rebels, the two armies meet on the Roman road of Watling Street, here, at the small settlement of Mancetter.

{Mancetter12}
There will be no quarter given.

{Mancetter13}
Boudicca has every reason to hate the Romans. 

{Mancetter14}
The Romans never, ever let rebels live. 

{Mancetter15}
Mancetter will decide whether Britannia is part of Rome, or returns to the old ways…

{Telamon01}
225BC and the bloody 1st Punic War is at and end.

{Telamon02}
The Romans have every right to feel pleased with the result: victory!

{Telamon03}
Rome now expects little resistance as she uses her might and influence.

{Telamon04}
The mere sight of her armies quashes any signs of opposition.

{Telamon05}
Peace, however, never seems to last. 

{Telamon06}
Gallic tribes and mercenaries have marched from Transalpine Gaul into Etruria through an unguarded pass in the Apennines.

{Telamon07}
To meet this invasion, the Romans have called on resources and manpower from across central and southern Italy.

{Telamon08}
A powerful defensive force has been rapidly mobilised.

{Telamon09}
They have outmanoeuvred the Gauls, forcing these barbarians towards the Tuscan coast. 

{Telamon10}
Meanwhile, a second Roman army has landed at Pisae. The Gauls now have no line of retreat. 

{Telamon11}
They are surrounded. Trapped. 

{Telamon12}
Assailed from both sides, the Gauls must fight for their very existence as a free people. 

{Telamon13}
Their only hope for survival is to quickly defeat the Roman forces in front of them -

{Telamon14}
- and then turn to deal with the Romans approaching from the rear -

{Telamon15}
- or their defeat is certain.

{Telamon16}
The Romans are veterans of many battles against the Gauls. They have no intention of letting them escape this time…

{Raphia01}
It is more than a century since the death of Alexander the Great.

{Raphia02}
His glorious empire has shattered into a number of warring successor kingdoms. 

{Raphia03}
In Egypt, Pharaoh Ptolemy IV, is a Greek ruler on the Egyptian throne.

{Raphia04}
He has not been a loved or respected ruler.

{Raphia05}
He is so popular that his Generals and Governors have gone over to the rival Seleucids.

{Raphia06}
The Seleucid king, Antiochus III, has designs on the border region of Coele-Syria, recently taken by Ptolemy.

{Raphia07}
With Egypt weakend by defections, Antiochus has marched to war near the town of Raphia. 

{Raphia08}
War now looms.

{Raphia09}
It is Spring in 217 BC, and the confrontation is nearing a climax. 

{Raphia10}
Diplomacy has delayed the fighting long enough.

{Raphia11}
Ptolemy's chariots and bowmen stand ready to unleash a storm of death upon the Seleucid ranks.

{Raphia12}
Antiochus hopes his powerful phalanx and swift cavalry will teach the Egyptians a bloody lesson.

{Raphia13}
Even though he is an experienced leader, Antiochus has been carried away by the thrill of a cavalry charge. He is cut off from the rest of his army.

{Raphia14}
The Seleucid king is in mortal danger, surrounded by enemies!

{Raphia15}
The battle now hangs in the balance.

{Raphia16}
Antiochus must regroup, or the Egyptians will carry the day!

{Lake_Trasimene01}
Rome is not the only power rising along the shores of the Mediterranean.

{Lake_Trasimene02}
Another people, the Carthaginians, have imperial ambitions. Their empire is growing in Spain, even as the Romans secure the Italian peninsular.

{Lake_Trasimene03}
Sooner or later a clash between the two powers was inevitable. Both have designs on the same lands, the same riches!

{Lake_Trasimene04}
For Rome, Caius Flaminius has been sent north to deal with the Carthaginian problem.

{Lake_Trasimene05}
And it is a problem: Hannibal Barca, the greatest Carthaginian general ever, is on the march.

{Lake_Trasimene06}
He swore an oath to his dying father that he would never give the Romans a moment's peace. 

{Lake_Trasimene07}
This is the year 218 BC.

{Lake_Trasimene08}
Hannibal has already kept his oath at Trebia. After that victory, he forced the Romans back onto the defensive.

{Lake_Trasimene09}
Now, with his army at Lake Trasimene, Hannibal plans to lure another Roman army into a brutal ambush. He has every reason to hope the Romans will cooperate in their own deaths!

{Lake_Trasimene10}
The Romans quickly move to meet the obvious threat from Hannibal's men. 

{Lake_Trasimene11}
Unaware of the danger, Flaminius orders his leading units to attack. 

{Lake_Trasimene12}
Hannibal springs his trap! His waiting troops are ordered to attack the unprepared Romans.

{Lake_Trasimene13}
The Carthaginian plan is to sweep down on the Roman flank, and drive their enemies into the icy waters of Lake Trasimene.

{Lake_Trasimene14}
Only courage and Roman discipline will save the Roman army -

{Lake_Trasimene15}
- The legionaries must turn and face the oncoming Carthaginians, and keep themselves from being surrounded!

{Syracuse00}
In centuries past, the city-state of Syracuse was a Greek colony on the island of Sicily

{Syracuse01}
It had been blessed with a highly defensible position, with imposing and impenetrable walls built to repel invaders.

{Syracuse02}
Many battles had been fought over this city, but it had finally managed to establish a dominance of its own in the Western Mediterranean.

{Syracuse03}
During the next hundred years, Carthage expanded its power once more into Sicily, and Syracuse turned to its allies of Greece and Rome to repel their influence.

{Syracuse04}
In 215 BC, Syracuse's alliance with Rome came to a shuddering halt with the death of their king, Hiero.

{Syracuse05}
With Syracuse declared a Rebublic, it became clear that the leading political party now supported Carthage.

{Syracuse06}
In a typically militaristic response, the Romans sent an invasion force under Claudius Marcellus to end the discussion.

{Syracuse07}
Marcellus moved immediately to besiege Syracuse. 

{Syracuse08}
In a long and bitter struggle, the Roman general eventually gained the upper hand by capturing the outer defences with an audacious night assault.

{Syracuse09}
The legendary walls of Syracuse have finally come within range of the Roman Onagers.

{Syracuse10}
If the Carthaginians can be beaten back from Syracuse, a vital strategic stronghold will be denied to them.

{Syracuse11}
Rome would edge one step closer to the Carthaginian homelands.

{Syracuse12}
Defend your city and drive back the Roman invaders…

{Syracuse13}
Attack the city and drive out the Carthaginian barbarians…

{Zama00}
After fifteen years of warfare, Carthage and Rome have fought each other almost to the point of exhaustion. 

{Zama01}
For the Carthaginians, The Second Punic War is not going well.

{Zama02}
Even the Roman legions are beginning to find that their resources are becoming stretched to the limit.

{Zama03}
Despite brilliant victories, Hannibal Barca has been unable to break the grip of Roman power in Italy. 

{Zama04}
The Romans however, have painfully learned how to tactically defeat Hannibal and his Carthaginian army on the battlefield.

{Zama05}
In 204BC, Publius Cornelius Scipio landed in North Africa at the head of a large Roman force. 

{Zama06}
Scipio is an outstanding general whose reforms to the Roman army have made him a legend.

{Zama07}
He is now in Hannibal's homeland, threatening destruction at the very heart of the Carthaginian Empire.

{Zama08}
However, with the urgent recall of Hannibal and his veterans from Italy, Carthage once again feel they have the upper hand.

{Zama09}
With any hope of peace now dead, Hannibal and Scipio have gathered their armies and marched to battle.

{Zama10}
Here they now stand, facing each other at Zama.

{Zama11}
The battle lines are drawn. 

{Zama12}
On one side, Scipio and his superbly trained army.

{Zama13}
On the other, Hannibal and his imposing contingent of elephants.

{Zama14}
With the loss of his Numidian allies, will the legendary Carthaginian's cavalry be able to withstand the might of Rome? 

{Magnesia00}
Antiochus II of the Seleucid Empire is making serious efforts to regain Asia Minor.

{Magnesia01}
Although the Romans have no direct interest in this part of the Mediterranean world, their allies do.

{Magnesia02}
As a result, the Romans begin to interfere, simply because any other great power might be a threat to Roman security.

{Magnesia03}
It is only a matter of time before fighting begins. 

{Magnesia04}
Neither side wished for a war, but in the charged atmosphere of Roman arrogance and Seleucid suspicion of Rome’s motives, it has become inevitable. 

{Magnesia05}
Magnesia, 190BC.

{Magnesia06}
The time for diplomacy is over and a more physical resolution is now called for.

{Magnesia07}
The Romans and Seleucids now stand facing each other, prepared for a bloody battle.

{Magnesia08}
Antiochus III has his troops formed up in large phalanxes, separated by elephants to make a more flexible battle line than a pure phalanx. 

{Magnesia09}
Every phalanx, of course, is vulnerable in the flanks, a problem made worse by the decline in the quality of Greek cavalry. 

{Magnesia10}
The Romans, for their part, are a supremely disciplined and flexible force.

{Magnesia11}
Against the mighty Roman legions, the Seleucid army looks to be tested to the very brink of destruction…

{Arausio01}
The year is 105 BC, and Rome's interference is about to lead to another war.

{Arausio02}
This is Gnaeus Mallius Maximus, commander of a well-trained Roman army, and consul of Rome.

{Arausio03}
With him is proconsul Quintus Servilius Caepio, an "ally" and rival for power.

{Arausio04}
They have come north to deal with - eradicate, in fact - the Cimbri and Teutone tribes beyond Rome's borders.

{Arausio05}
For Rome's borders are soon to expand.

{Arausio06}
The barbarians occupy land that should, by right of arms, be Roman.

{Arausio07}
But the Cimbri and Teutones are not going anywhere.

{Arausio08}
Loot that should have gone to fill the coffers of Rome. 

{Arausio09}
Gnaeus Mallius Maximus and his army are in Transalpine Gaul.

{Arausio10}
As the Romans approach the barbarians Quintus Servilius Caepio looks to his own interests. His army pulls back.

{Arausio11}
Gnaeus Mallius Maximus now has a flank of his army exposed.

{Arausio12}
The huge barbarian force stands ready to crush the weakened Roman force.

{Arausio13}
The Romans are in trouble. 

{Arausio14}
Maximus is surrounded, and could be swept away by the barbarian hordes. 

{Arausio15}
His only hope is to hold out until reinforcements come.

{Arausio16}
He must find a strong, defensible position to withstand the Cimbri and Teutones -

{Arausio17}
- or Roman honour and Roman lives will be lost.

{Jugurtha00}
Numidia had been a Carthaginian client kingdom for many centuries.

{Jugurtha01}
During the Second Punic War however, Numidia swapped sides, abandoning Carthage in favour of Rome. 

{Jugurtha02}
They spent decades extending their influence, stealing former Carthaginian territory and trying to turn their people into settled peasants. 

{Jugurtha03}
The fleeing Carthaginians were allowed to settle in what are now Numidian lands. 

{Jugurtha04}
Seeds of trouble had been sown, however.

{Jugurtha05}
The new King, Micipsa, adopted his nephew, Jugurtha as an heir. 

{Jugurtha06}
Jugurtha was given command of the Numidian forces and sent to help the Romans.

{Jugurtha07}
He quickly impressed many of them with his military prowess.

{Jugurtha08}
When Micipsa died, Jugurtha usurped the throne and promptly broke free from the Roman alliance.

{Jugurtha09}
Matters should have rested there, but Jugurtha allowed himself to be provoked by Roman politicking.

{Jugurtha10}
It is 109BC, and the upstart Numidian has declared war against his former Roman allies.

{Jugurtha11}
Rome, never one to take threats lightly, has sent the best soldier the Empire has ever produced.

{Jugurtha12}
This man had been elected consul in consecutive years – something that wasn’t supposed to happen under Roman law.

{Jugurtha13}
The man they sent was Gaius Marius…

{Chaeronea00}
It is 86BC.

{Chaeronea01}
A period of Roman political unrest is causing division within the Senate.

{Chaeronea02}
Taking advantage of the Roman turmoil, Pontus has emerged as an Empire to be reckoned with. 

{Chaeronea03}
In particular, Mithradates the VI of Pontus has emerged as an ambitious man.

{Chaeronea04}
Setting his sights firmly on the territories of the Roman Empire, he swiftly mobilises his forces.

{Chaeronea05}
Leading from the head of his armies, Mithradates has begun to move west through Asia Minor into Roman territory. 

{Chaeronea06}
Lucius Cornelius Sulla began his military career in Africa, under the now famous general Gaius Marius.

{Chaeronea07}
After helping in the capture of Jugurtha of Numidia, he eventually became consul as a member of the senatorial group.

{Chaeronea08}
Seeing it as an opportunity to prove his worth as a general, Sulla has prepared his forces to crush Mithradates and Pontus once and for all.

{Chaeronea09}
His legions now stand ready. 

{Chaeronea10}
Across the field of battle awaits the upstart Mithradates of Pontus, intent on crushing the Romans.

{Chaeronea11}
Mithradates holds the higher ground and has numerical superiority.

{Chaeronea12}
Sulla's troops are battle hardened veterans, some of the most capable soldiers Rome has ever produced.

{Chaeronea13}
Two Empires.

{Chaeronea14}
Two Men.

{Chaeronea15}
Only one Empire can survive this battle…

{Gergovia01}
Julius Caesar is, by any definition, a successful Roman general and politician.

{Gergovia02}
In a series of brilliant campaigns, he has defeated many Gallic tribes and brought new lands into the Roman empire.

{Gergovia03}
His Roman legionaries - veterans of many battles - take pride in their skill and valour.

{Gergovia04}
But in 54 BC his good luck ran out. 

{Gergovia05}
Vercingetorix, the leader of the Avernii tribe, has revolted against Roman rule.

{Gergovia06}
For once, Caesar has been overtaken by events, forced to react, rather than forge his own destiny.

{Gergovia07}
It is now one year later, and the rebellion is not yet crushed.

{Gergovia08}
At Gergovia, the Gauls are ready, watching the Roman army on a nearby hill.

{Gergovia09}
Wary of being ambushed, Caesar has sent Roman legionaries to the far side of Gergovia to watch for any encircling enemies.

{Gergovia10}
But the Gauls are equally suspicious, and send their entire army to watch over the marching Romans.

{Gergovia11}
Too far from the main army to allow reinforcement, the small Roman detachment is ambushed and destroyed by Gallic warriors. 

{Gergovia12}
Seeing that the Gauls have abandoned their camp, Caesar orders his troops towards the fort. 

{Gergovia13}
As the news of Caesar's attack reaches the Gauls, they move to counter the Romans.

{Gergovia14}
And Caesar, in turn, recognises the new danger and sounds the retreat.

{Gergovia15}
But the legions appear not to have heard their new orders.

{Gergovia16}
Instead, the Romans charge the fort!

{Gergovia17}
Caesar's men suddenly find themselves on dangerous ground, surrounded by angry Gauls.

{Gergovia18}
The ram must be protected if the Romans are to take the fort.

{Gergovia19}
Perhaps then the tables can be turned on the barbarians. 

{Alexandria00}
After his crushing defeat at Pharsalus, Caesar's rival Pompey decided that a trip to Egypt would be beneficial to his continuing good health. 

{Alexandria01}
He fled to the Egyptian city of Alexandria by sea, looking for asylum with the Egyptian ruler, Ptolemy XIII.

{Alexandria02}
Before Pompey could land however, he was assassinated.

{Alexandria03}
Caesar, hot in pursuit, arrived shortly afterwards and was soon deeply involved in Egyptian politics and Ptolemaic family squabblings.

{Alexandria04}
It became clear Ptolemy XIII was not the only member of his family to have designs on the throne of Egypt.

{Alexandria05}
His sister-and-wife, Cleopatra VII, had thoughts of being queen all by herself. 

{Alexandria06}
The 22-year-old had herself delivered to Caesar's quarters wrapped in an oriental carpet.

{Alexandria07}
Cleopatra used her beguiling beauty to persuade Ceasar into supporting her instead of her brother. 

{Alexandria08}
Her plan worked, and with the recent arrival of Roman reinforcements, Caesar now plans to carry out a coup on her behalf.

{Alexandria09}
Ceasar's troops stand ready to engage Ptolemy's loyalists in brutal combat through the streets of Alexandria.

{Alexandria10}
The prize for the loser will be a violent death.

{Alexandria11}
To the winner goes Alexandria and Egypt.

{Alexandria12}
The greatest prize of all, however, is the alluringly beautiful Cleopatra.

{Alexandria13}
Only one man can win.

{Alexandria14}
Only one man can claim Cleopatra as his queen.

{Alexandria15}
Kill Ptolemy and claim the city for the glory of Rome…

{Bibracte00}
When the Romans arrived in Transalpine Gaul they lost no time in becoming involved in local Celtic politics. 

{Bibracte01}
This meant that many of the Celtic tribes were gradually drawn into the Roman sphere of influence as trade and wealth seduced them.

{Bibracte02}
The Aedui were one such tribe.

{Bibracte03}
Indeed, they were even given the title of 'Friends of Rome' by the Senate to show the close relationship. 

{Bibracte04}
It was natural, then, that the Aedui would turn to the Romans for help when they were under pressure from their aggressive, land-hungry neighbours.

{Bibracte05}
The Helvetii were a Gallic tribe who had begun to move out of the mountains and into Aedui lands. 

{Bibracte06}
Initially the Senate declined to help.

{Bibracte07}
Julius Ceasar however, had recently been appointed proconsul.

{Bibracte08}
He immediately recognised the opportunity for expanding direct Roman control into Gaul.

{Bibracte09}
He agreed to help, seeing this as a chance to move his armies into Celtic territory, and marched northwards at the head of his troops.

{Bibracte10}
If the Helvetii could be defeated, little would stand between Caesar and the rest of Gaul...

{MonsGraupius01}
This is 84 AD. 

{MonsGraupius02}
The far north of Britannia is mostly at peace. 

{MonsGraupius03}
But in the remote mountains at the edge of the Roman world, a few men still resist Roman power.

{MonsGraupius04}
Agricola, the Roman governor of Britannia, has come north with his army to bring peace to these dark hills.

{MonsGraupius05}
Once and for all, Roman authority will control the highlands and the wild, blue-painted men who live there.

{MonsGraupius06}
The Britons have chosen the ground for their last stand: Mons Graupius.

{MonsGraupius07}
The steep, high ground gives the Britons an advantage.

{MonsGraupius08}
Agricola and his legions are now upon them.

{MonsGraupius09}
Agricola will need to lure the Britons off the slope if he is to win, perhaps encircling them in the process.

{MonsGraupius10}
The last bastion of British freedom is about to be assaulted. 

{MonsGraupius11}
This is a final, bloody day of reckoning.

{MonsGraupius12}
The freedom of Britannnia's Highlands is about to face the most deadly test yet.

{MonsGraupius13}
Perhaps the final, bloody test…

{Tigranocerta01}
Tigranocerta: the capital of the Armenia King, Tigranes.

{Tigranocerta02}
He is a proud man, and rightfully so.

{Tigranocerta03}
He also hates Rome. And perhaps fears what Rome will do.

{Tigranocerta04}
For years, he has allied himself with the King of Pontus, defying Rome in all things.

{Tigranocerta05}
By 69 BC Roman patience was at an end. Lucullus Sulla was sent east to settle scores.

{Tigranocerta06}
Now Pontus is too weak to aid Tigranes. He must face the storm on his own.

{Tigranocerta07}
But no matter. Tigranes is a man set on victory.

{Tigranocerta08}
With his fearsome cataphract cavalry, he knows the Armenians are better soldiers than the Romans.

{Tigranocerta09}
And so here, across the river, he has moved to face Lucullus Sulla.

{Tigranocerta10}
In response, the Romans have moved along the river bank, a tactical retreat.

{Tigranocerta11}
Suddenly Sulla orders a charge across the ford, taking on the right flank of the Armenian army where the cataphracts are posted.

{Tigranocerta12}
The Romans hope to work around the flank and continue the attack.

{Tigranocerta13}
Tigranes is surprised, outflanked and facing the most efficient army in the world. The Armenians are on the edge of panicking.

{Tigranocerta14}
If Tigranes is to win today, he must hold the high ground and control the ford.

{Tigranocerta15}
There is now little that can save Armenia from falling into ruin and becoming one of history's forgotten glories…

{Siege_of_Sparta01}
King Pyrrhus' life is an epic tale of his rise to power, of tragic loss and outrageous misfortune. 
So much so, that his name gives us the saying "Pyrrhic Victory". 
He won a victory against Rome in 279 BC, but at an enormous - almost crippling - cost.

{Siege_of_Sparta02}
That was seven years ago. Now Pyrrhus has raised a mighty army to take Greece and - after some early success - he heads to the city of Sparta. 
The home of the heroes of Thermopylae.

{Siege_of_Sparta03}
Word has reached Pyrrhus that Sparta is ill defended.

{Siege_of_Sparta04}
King Areus of Sparta and many of his best warrioirs are away fighting in Crete and only a small force is present.

{Siege_of_Sparta05}
What better time is there to attack?
A city with most of its army away on campaign is an easy target.

{Siege_of_Sparta06}
Little does Pyrrhus know, but even a handful of Spartan youths and Helot slaves can put up a heroic struggle -

{Siege_of_Sparta07}
- and what is more, reinforcements are on their way!

{Siege_of_Sparta08}
Pyrrhus must take the city now - and take it quickly!

{Battle_of_Asculum01}
It is the early 3rd century BC and the military prestige of the Greek Successors has reached its zenith in the person of King Pyrrhus of Epirus. 

{Battle_of_Asculum02}
But the fledgling state of Rome is trying to secure her supremacy on Italian soil. 

{Battle_of_Asculum03}
The two cultures are about to clash: at Asculum, in south east Italy.

{Battle_of_Asculum04}
After a day of inconclusive fighting in the forests and hills, Pyrrhus manoeuvres the Romans into a head-on battle where his forces must win the day.

{Battle_of_Asculum05}
Elephants and Phalanxes against the Legions of Rome. 

{Battle_of_Asculum06}
Can the Romans hold the field against the best Greece has to offer? Or will they crumble and flee?

¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************
¬*
¬*			THIS FILE GONE FOR LOCALISATION!!!
¬*		ALL CHANGES & ADDITIONS MADE POST THE DATE SPECIFIED 
¬*			BELOW MUST GO UNDERNEATH THIS DIVIDER!!!
¬*
¬*		This particular divider does not denote a changes round.
¬*	This is when the files were locked to be sent for Russian and Polish translation.
¬*
¬*
¬***** Changes made after 01/07/2004 09:00:00
¬*
¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************

¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************
¬*
¬*			THIS FILE GONE FOR LOCALISATION!!!
¬*		ALL CHANGES & ADDITIONS MADE POST THE DATE SPECIFIED 
¬*			BELOW MUST GO UNDERNEATH THIS DIVIDER!!!
¬*
¬*
¬***** Changes made after 07/07/2004 17:15:00
¬*
¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************

¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************
¬*
¬*			THIS FILE GONE FOR LOCALISATION!!!
¬*		ALL CHANGES & ADDITIONS MADE POST THE DATE SPECIFIED 
¬*			BELOW MUST GO UNDERNEATH THIS DIVIDER!!!
¬*
¬*
¬***** Changes made after 15/07/2004 17:00:00
¬*
¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************

¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************
¬*
¬*			THIS FILE GONE FOR LOCALISATION!!!
¬*		ALL CHANGES & ADDITIONS MADE POST THE DATE SPECIFIED 
¬*			BELOW MUST GO UNDERNEATH THIS DIVIDER!!!
¬*
¬*
¬***** Changes made after 22/07/2004 09:00:00
¬*
¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************

¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************
¬*
¬*			THIS FILE GONE FOR LOCALISATION!!!
¬*		ALL CHANGES & ADDITIONS MADE POST THE DATE SPECIFIED 
¬*			BELOW MUST GO UNDERNEATH THIS DIVIDER!!!
¬*
¬*
¬***** Changes made after 29/07/2004 09:00:00
¬*
¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************

¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************
¬*
¬*			THIS FILE GONE FOR LOCALISATION!!!
¬*		ALL CHANGES & ADDITIONS MADE POST THE DATE SPECIFIED 
¬*			BELOW MUST GO UNDERNEATH THIS DIVIDER!!!
¬*
¬*
¬***** Changes made after 05/08/2004 12:00:00
¬*
¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************

¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************
¬*
¬*			THIS FILE GONE FOR LOCALISATION!!!
¬*		ALL CHANGES & ADDITIONS MADE POST THE DATE SPECIFIED 
¬*			BELOW MUST GO UNDERNEATH THIS DIVIDER!!!
¬*
¬*
¬***** Changes made after 12/08/2004 09:53:00
¬*
¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************

¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************
¬*
¬*			THIS FILE GONE FOR LOCALISATION!!!
¬*		ALL CHANGES & ADDITIONS MADE POST THE DATE SPECIFIED 
¬*			BELOW MUST GO UNDERNEATH THIS DIVIDER!!!
¬*
¬*
¬***** Changes made after 19/08/2004 16:05:00
¬*
¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************

¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************
¬*
¬*			THIS FILE GONE FOR LOCALISATION!!!
¬*		ALL CHANGES & ADDITIONS MADE POST THE DATE SPECIFIED 
¬*			BELOW MUST GO UNDERNEATH THIS DIVIDER!!!
¬*
¬*
¬***** Changes made after 01/09/2004 09:00:00
¬*
¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************

¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************
¬*
¬*			THIS FILE GONE FOR LOCALISATION!!!
¬*		ALL CHANGES & ADDITIONS MADE POST THE DATE SPECIFIED 
¬*			BELOW MUST GO UNDERNEATH THIS DIVIDER!!!
¬*
¬*
¬***** Changes made after 03/09/2004 09:00:00
¬*
¬****************************************************************************************
¬****************************************************************************************

¬+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++
¬*******************************************************************************************************
¬*******************************************************************************************************
¬*
¬*			EXPANSION PACK TEXT BEGINS HERE!!!
¬*		ALL TEXT BELOW THIS LINE SHOULD BE EXPANSION ADDITIONS/CHANGES ONLY!!!
¬*
¬*¬***** Changes made after 05/01/2005 15:18:00
¬*
¬*******************************************************************************************************
¬*******************************************************************************************************
¬+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++