¬
{Prologue_Agent_Basics_Text_01_Text1}As well as controlling armies and building settlements, you will also need to use various agents to carry out your plans. There is an assassin named George waiting for your orders near Nottingham. Left-click on him to select him now.
{Prologue_Agent_Basics_Text_01_Title}Agents 
{Prologue_Assassin_Basics_Text_01_Text1}Your assassin can assassinate important foreign figures and sabotage buildings in foreign settlements. Right-click on Angus Macdougall, the nearby Scottish diplomat, to attempt an assassination.
{Prologue_Assassin_Basics_Text_01_Title}Assassins 
{Prologue_Assassination_Basics_Text_01_Text1}This scroll shows your chances of succeeding in the assassination. Diplomats and less important people are easier to kill, whereas kings will provide a greater challenge. This man is an easy target, left-click the 'Accept mission' button to assassinate him.
{Prologue_Assassination_Basics_Text_01_Title}Assassination 
{Prologue_Assassination_Failed_Text_01_Text1}Even the most skilled assassins miss sometimes. You can make another attempt on this man's life next turn.
{Prologue_Assassination_Failed_Text_01_Title}Escaped Assassination 
{Prologue_Assassination_Not_Ordered_Text_01_Text1}Your assassin is waiting for your command to carry out the assassination. To order the assassination, right-click on the target and click the 'Accept mission' button on the right of the scroll.
{Prologue_Assassination_Not_Ordered_Text_01_Title}Assassination Order 
{Prologue_Assassination_Success_Text_01_Text1}Congratulations! Your assassin has delivered this man the fate that he deserved.
{Prologue_Assassination_Success_Text_01_Title}Assassination Success! 
{Prologue_Attack_Nottingham_Text_01_Text1}Your siege equipment has been constructed and some catapults have arrived from Normandy to reinforce your army. You are now ready to siege Nottingham. To attack the castle, select William and his army and right-click on Nottingham. Click the 'Assault' button to begin the siege.
{Prologue_Attack_Nottingham_Text_01_Title}Attack Nottingham 
{Prologue_Board_the_Fleet_Text_01_Text1}Select Rufus and right-click on the nearby fleet to board it.
{Prologue_Board_the_Fleet_Text_01_Title}Board the Fleet 
{Prologue_Build_Church_Completed_Text_01_Text1}You have successfully completed your mission from the Pope. He now regards you more highly for complying with his wishes.
{Prologue_Build_Church_Completed_Text_01_Title}Mission Completed 
{Prologue_Build_Church_Text_01_Text1}To carry out your mission, order a church to be constructed by left-clicking on the picture of the church.
{Prologue_Build_Church_Text_01_Title}Build a Church 
{Prologue_Building_Browser_Text_01_Text1}Left-click on the 'Show building browser' button on the bottom of the scroll to view the buildings that are available in a castle. In cities, such as London, different buildings are available for construction.
{Prologue_Building_Browser_Text_01_Title}Building Browser 
{Prologue_Caen_Under_Siege_Text_01_Text1}The rebel army is assaulting Caen! We have a superior army and should sally forth to attack them. Sallying out is the only way to break a siege, preventing your men from starving and allowing the settlement to resume construction and recruitment.
{Prologue_Caen_Under_Siege_Text_01_Title}Caen Under Siege 
{Prologue_Campaign_HUD_Text_01_Text1}The panel at the bottom of the screen gives you information about your armies and settlements. The panel on the right has buttons for construction, recruitment, ending your turn, and viewing information on your faction and progress.
{Prologue_Campaign_HUD_Text_01_Title}Campaign UI 
{Prologue_Campaign_Turns_Text_01_Text1}The campaign progresses in turns. Each turn there is a limit to the distance your characters can move and the troops you can recruit. Your agents can only carry out one mission per turn and each of your buildings take a certain number of turns to construct.
{Prologue_Campaign_Turns_Text_01_Title}Campaign Turns 
{Prologue_Capturing_a_Settlement_Text_01_Text1}When you capture a settlement, you have the option to Occupy, Sack or Exterminate. Occupying a settlement brings it under your rule peacefully, but the people might rebel against you. Sacking allows your troops to loot and pillage, which gives an order and cash bonus, but buildings are damaged and people are killed. Exterminating kills most of the population and reduces the level of the buildings, but brings the population under your control.
{Prologue_Capturing_a_Settlement_Text_01_Title}Capturing a Settlement 
{Prologue_Castle_Basics_Text_01_Text1}Castles differ from cities in the buildings you can construct and the units you can recruit. Your castles will be your unit-production centres. Castles produce little income, but are easier to manage than cities. You will need a balance of castles and cities to ensure you can support your troops.
{Prologue_Castle_Basics_Text_01_Title}Castle Basics 
{Prologue_Church_In_Queue_Text_01_Text1}Your church has been added to the construction queue and takes one turn to build, so it will be completed next turn.
{Prologue_Church_In_Queue_Text_01_Title}Church Under Construction 
{Prologue_City_Basics_Text_01_Text1}London is a city, which means it is a hub for trade and will generate your income. It is important to keep the people in your cities happy. Left-click on the 'Show settlement details' button at the bottom of the scroll to see important information about your city and people.
{Prologue_City_Basics_Text_01_Title}City Basics 
{Prologue_City_Details_Text_01_Text1}This scroll shows you a breakdown of important factors affecting your settlement. Move the mouse cursor over each icon to find out more information. In cities, your main aims are to maximise income and growth, while keeping public order and religion as high as possible. Close the Settlement Details scroll when you are ready.
{Prologue_City_Details_Text_01_Title}City Details 
{Prologue_Diplomatic_Standing_Text_01_Text1}This scroll enables you to view the state of diplomatic relations between each faction at a glance. Use this scroll to aid you in making and breaking alliances during your campaign.
{Prologue_Diplomatic_Standing_Text_01_Title}Diplomatic Standing 
{Prologue_End_Turn_2_Text_01_Text1}Your siege equipment takes time to build. End your turn and you will be able to attack the settlement next turn. To end your turn, press the hourglass button on the bottom-right of the screen.
{Prologue_End_Turn_2_Text_01_Title}End Turn 
{Prologue_End_Turn_3_Text_01_Text1}Your units will take time to train. Press the 'End Turn' button and your new troops will be ready next turn.
{Prologue_End_Turn_3_Text_01_Title}End Turn 
{Prologue_End_Turn_4_Text_01_Text1}Press the 'End Turn' button to end your turn when you are ready.
{Prologue_End_Turn_4_Text_01_Title}End Turn 
{Prologue_Event_Message_Text_01_Text1}The boxes that slide down the left of the screen are important messages. Left-click on a message to open it.
{Prologue_Event_Message_Text_01_Title}Event Messages 
{Prologue_Faction_Finances_Text_01_Text1}You can review the state of your faction's finances here. Your current treasury is also permanently displayed below the 'End Turn' button at the bottom right of the screen.
{Prologue_Faction_Finances_Text_01_Title}Faction Finances 
{Prologue_Faction_Overview_Text_01_Text1}This scroll shows a summary of important information about your faction and progress through the game.
{Prologue_Faction_Overview_Text_01_Title}Faction Overview 
{Prologue_Faction_Summary_Text_01_Text1}You can view important details about your faction, finances and diplomatic standing via the Overview panel. To open the Overview panel, left-click on the button with your faction symbol on it at the bottom-right of the screen.
{Prologue_Faction_Summary_Text_01_Title}Faction Summary 
{Prologue_Fleet_Basics_Text_01_Text1}Each fleet has a character card, shown on the bottom panel of the screen. If you click the Army tab on this panel, you will see the units that are present aboard your fleet.
{Prologue_Fleet_Basics_Text_01_Title}Fleet Basics 
{Prologue_Fleet_Movement_Text_01_Text1}You can move your fleet by right-clicking anywhere in the highlighted zone. Right-clicking on the coast will disembark your army. Right-click on Normandy's coast now to disembark.
{Prologue_Fleet_Movement_Text_01_Title}Fleet Movement 
{Prologue_Fortify_Caen_Text_01_Text1}William the Conqueror's next goal is to take over England. Before you do this, you will need to move Rufus back to Normandy to fortify Caen.
{Prologue_Fortify_Caen_Text_01_Title}Reinforce and Conquer 
{Prologue_Hastings_Archers_Firing_Text_01_Text1}When your archers are firing on the enemy, a bow and arrow icon appears on the top-left of their unit card. When you order your archers to fire, they will move into range and then attack.
{Prologue_Hastings_Archers_Firing_Text_01_Title}Archers Firing 
{Prologue_Hastings_Attack_Huscarls_Text_01_Text1}Harold's most brave and loyal troops, his Huscarls, are still standing to fight. Help William finish them off and be done with this bloody day!
{Prologue_Hastings_Attack_Huscarls_Text_01_Title}Finish Them! 
{Prologue_Hastings_Attack_Shield_Wall_Text_01_Text1}Without the peasants, the Saxon shield wall is broken and their position is weak! Order your archers to fire into the Saxon infantry now!
{Prologue_Hastings_Attack_Shield_Wall_Text_01_Title}Attack the Shield Wall! 
{Prologue_Hastings_Attack_With_Archers_Text_01_Text1}Move your mouse cursor over the approaching Saxons and right-click to attack when your cursor changes to a bow.
{Prologue_Hastings_Attack_With_Archers_Text_01_Title}Attack with Archers 
{Prologue_Hastings_Attack_With_Infantry_Text_01_Text1}Your Armoured Sergeants are your best melee fighters. Select these spearmen now and attack the Saxons. To attack, mouse over the Saxons and right-click when your cursor changes to a sword.
{Prologue_Hastings_Attack_With_Infantry_Text_01_Title}Attack with Spearmen 
{Prologue_Hastings_Banners_Text_01_Text1}Each of your units proudly bears the Norman banner. You can easily recognise your men on the battlefield by this banner. Different types of units have differently shaped banners. You can also select a unit by clicking on their banner.
{Prologue_Hastings_Banners_Text_01_Title}Troop Banners 
{Prologue_Hastings_Battle_Advisor_Text_01_Text1}Well met, Commander! I am Sir Robert, your military advisor. I will watch your actions on the battlefield and guide you to glory. Follow my instructions and we will crush these Saxon dogs!
{Prologue_Hastings_Battle_Advisor_Text_01_Title}Military Advisor 
{Prologue_Hastings_Battle_HUD_Text_01_Text1}The panel at the bottom of the screen shows a map of the battlefield, an indicator of your progress in the battle, controls for the pace of the battle, your general and troops, as well as options and commands for your selected forces.
{Prologue_Hastings_Battle_HUD_Text_01_Title}Battle Interface 
{Prologue_Hastings_Battle_Speed_Bridge_Text_01_Text1}When you have ordered your troops to move a long distance, you can increase the game speed to get them into position faster. Set the battle to the highest speed now by clicking the 'Faster' button twice.
{Prologue_Hastings_Battle_Speed_Bridge_Text_01_Title}Battle Speed 
{Prologue_Hastings_Battle_Speed_Form_Up_Text_01_Text1}Now is a good time to use the speed controls to move your troops into position faster. Set the battle to the highest speed now and back to normal speed when they're almost in position.
{Prologue_Hastings_Battle_Speed_Form_Up_Text_01_Title}Battle Speed 
{Prologue_Hastings_Called_Into_Main_Battle_Text_01_Text1}William has called for you to join the main battle. The end of the battle is at hand and the next few moments will determine the fate of England.
{Prologue_Hastings_Called_Into_Main_Battle_Text_01_Title}Join the Battle 
{Prologue_Hastings_Cavalry_Run_Text_01_Text1}To get your units somewhere quickly, double right-click on a location. Order your cavalry to run by double right-clicking on the highlighted area.
{Prologue_Hastings_Cavalry_Run_Text_01_Title}Moving Quickly 
{Prologue_Hastings_Change_Unit_Speed_Text_01_Text1}You can change your units' speed of movement by pressing the unit speed toggle button on the bottom right panel. Try this now to order your cavalry to slow down.
{Prologue_Hastings_Change_Unit_Speed_Text_01_Title}Changing Speed 
{Prologue_Hastings_Chase_Routers_Text_01_Text1}Use your cavalry to chase down the routing troops. Your cavalry are fast and will catch the infantry easily. The fewer men you leave alive, the fewer you will have to deal with later.
{Prologue_Hastings_Chase_Routers_Text_01_Title}Chase the Routers! 
{Prologue_Hastings_Click_And_Drag_Text_01_Text1}You can order your units to move into formation by holding down the right mouse button and dragging out a line on the terrain where you want them to move.
{Prologue_Hastings_Click_And_Drag_Text_01_Title}Move into Formation 
{Prologue_Hastings_Cross_The_Bridge_Text_01_Text1}First, you need to move your army into the main battle. Press Ctrl-A to select all your units or hold down Ctrl and click each unit card. Then right-click on the far side of the crossing to move your units there.
{Prologue_Hastings_Cross_The_Bridge_Text_01_Title}Join the Battle 
{Prologue_Hastings_Deselect_All_Units_Text_01_Text1}You can easily deselect your selected units by pressing ENTER. Try this now.
{Prologue_Hastings_Deselect_All_Units_Text_01_Title}Deselect All Units 
{Prologue_Hastings_Double_Click_To_Pan_Text_01_Text1}Double left-clicking on a unit card centres your view on that unit. Double left-click on your cavalry's unit card now.
{Prologue_Hastings_Double_Click_To_Pan_Text_01_Title}Pan to Unit 
{Prologue_Hastings_Fire_On_Peasants_Text_01_Text1}William has ordered all archers to fire at the approaching peasants. Select your archers and fire at the nearest peasants!
{Prologue_Hastings_Fire_On_Peasants_Text_01_Title}Fire on the Peasants! 
{Prologue_Hastings_Friendly_Fire_Text_01_Text1}If your archers fire on a unit that is in melee with your own unit, your unit will take friendly fire from your archers. Select your archers and press the halt button to stop them firing.
{Prologue_Hastings_Friendly_Fire_Text_01_Title}Friendly Fire 
{Prologue_Hastings_Generals_Text_01_Text1}Your general is your most important unit. He commands your armies on the battlefield, giving them strength and courage to fight. When he is lost, your battle is lost. Remember, you must keep Rufus alive to conquer the Saxons.
{Prologue_Hastings_Generals_Text_01_Title}Generals 
{Prologue_Hastings_Halt_Orders_Text_01_Text1}You can press the 'Stop current orders' button on the bottom right panel to remove all current orders from your selected units. Press the 'Stop current orders' button now to stop your cavalry.
{Prologue_Hastings_Halt_Orders_Text_01_Title}Halt Orders 
{Prologue_Hastings_Infantry_Attack_Peasants_Text_01_Text1}Now run your Armoured Sergeants in to finish off those peasants. These spearmen are highly skilled in melee and are well-suited to close combat. Remember to stop your archers firing on the enemy or your spearmen will suffer unnecessary casualties.
{Prologue_Hastings_Infantry_Attack_Peasants_Text_01_Title}Attack with Spearmen 
{Prologue_Hastings_King_Harold_Dead_Text_01_Text1}King Harold has been caught by an arrow! The Saxon king is slain! His men have lost hope and they are fleeing.
{Prologue_Hastings_King_Harold_Dead_Text_01_Title}King Harold is Dead! 
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_All_Units_Text_01_Text1}Now that all your units are selected and awaiting your orders, move them to the highlighted area.
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_All_Units_Text_01_Title}Move All Units 
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_General_Text_01_Text1}You can move your armies around by right-clicking where you want them to go. Right-click on the highlighted area to move Rufus there.
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_General_Text_01_Title}Movement 
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_Into_Position_2_Text_01_Text1}Now order your spearmen to move into the second row.
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_Into_Position_2_Text_01_Title}Move into Position 
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_Into_Position_3_Text_01_Text1}Now order your general to fall in behind your troops.
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_Into_Position_3_Text_01_Title}Move Rufus into Position 
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_Into_Position_4_Text_01_Text1}Then move your cavalry into the third row.
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_Into_Position_4_Text_01_Title}Move into Position 
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_Into_Position_Text_01_Text1}William has given the order for your troops to fall into line with the rest of the Norman army. First, order your archers into the front row.
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_Into_Position_Text_01_Title}Move into Position 
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_View_RTS_Text_01_Text1}You will notice that your general has moved, but your view has not. Use the number pad on the keyboard to move your view of the battlefield. 5 and 2 will move it forward and back, 4 and 6 will move it sideways, and 1 and 3 will rotate your view. Move your view now so that Rufus is centred.
{Prologue_Hastings_Move_View_RTS_Text_01_Title}Move View 
{Prologue_Hastings_Normans_Flee_Text_01_Text1}Some of William's army have broken away and are fleeing! Units rout on the battlefield when their morale becomes very low. Morale decreases when units become tired, when their chance of success is low or if the general dies.
{Prologue_Hastings_Normans_Flee_Text_01_Title}Normans are Fleeing! 
{Prologue_Hastings_Pause_Game_Text_01_Text1}The battle is now paused. You can pause the battle at any time and issue orders to your troops. When you resume the battle, they will carry out your orders. Press the 'Play' button when you are ready to resume the battle.
{Prologue_Hastings_Pause_Game_Text_01_Title}Issuing Orders 
{Prologue_Hastings_Peasants_Charging_Text_01_Text1}The Saxon peasants have broken rank and are charging at us! They have seen our fleeing men and have made themselves vulnerable. Now is the time to attack!
{Prologue_Hastings_Peasants_Charging_Text_01_Title}Peasants are Charging! 
{Prologue_Hastings_Post_Battle_Demo_Text_01_Text1}Bravo, milord! You have slain King Harold and sent these Saxons running for their worthless lives! In Medieval 2: Total War, you will be able to lead William the Conqueror in his campaign to capture the English throne … then onwards to glory!
{Prologue_Hastings_Post_Battle_Demo_Text_01_Title}Hastings Won! 
{Prologue_Hastings_Post_Battle_Text_01_Text1}Bravo, milord! You have slain King Harold and sent these Saxons running for their worthless lives! You can review your men's performance in the battle here, before moving on with your campaign to seize England.
{Prologue_Hastings_Post_Battle_Text_01_Title}Hastings Won! 
{Prologue_Hastings_Quitting_Text_01_Text1}In order to complete the tutorial you must win this battle. If you quit now, you will lose any progress and will need to start over.
{Prologue_Hastings_Quitting_Text_01_Title}Quitting the Tutorial 
{Prologue_Hastings_Radar_Text_01_Text1}The small map on the bottom-left of the screen shows the location of all the units in the battle. You can use this map to easily locate your men and the enemy. Your units are green, allied units are blue and enemy units are red. You can double left-click a location on the map to move your view there immediately.
{Prologue_Hastings_Radar_Text_01_Title}Radar 
{Prologue_Hastings_Run_Down_With_Cavalry_Text_01_Text1}Now select your cavalry and double right-click on the enemy to run them down. Using your cavalry to stampede archers and infantry is a useful tactic.
{Prologue_Hastings_Run_Down_With_Cavalry_Text_01_Title}Cavalry Charge 
{Prologue_Hastings_Saxon_Reinforcements_Text_01_Text1}Some Saxon reinforcements have arrived! You must stop them from crossing the river and flanking the Norman army!
{Prologue_Hastings_Saxon_Reinforcements_Text_01_Title}Saxon Reinforcements! 
{Prologue_Hastings_Select_All_Units_Text_01_Text1}You can easily select all your units on the battlefield by pressing Ctrl-A. Try doing this now.
{Prologue_Hastings_Select_All_Units_Text_01_Title}Select All Units 
{Prologue_Hastings_Select_Archers_Text_01_Text1}Use your archers first, so you can weaken the Saxon infantry as they approach. Select your archers now.
{Prologue_Hastings_Select_Archers_Text_01_Title}Select your Archers 
{Prologue_Hastings_Select_Cavalry_Card_Text_01_Text1}You can also select your units by left-clicking on their character cards in the panel at the bottom of the screen. Left-click on your cavalry's unit card now to select them.
{Prologue_Hastings_Select_Cavalry_Card_Text_01_Title}Character Cards 
{Prologue_Hastings_Select_Rufus_Text_01_Text1}This is Rufus, your general on the battlefield. He is accompanied by an entourage of the finest Norman knights. Left-click on his unit to select them now.
{Prologue_Hastings_Select_Rufus_Text_01_Title}Select Rufus 
{Prologue_Hastings_Slow_Speed_Text_01_Text1}When your troops are nearing their destination, press the 'Slower' button twice to return the battle to normal speed. Otherwise, you might miss important events in the battle.
{Prologue_Hastings_Slow_Speed_Text_01_Title}Normal Speed 
{Prologue_Hastings_Tilt_Camera_RTS_Text_01_Text1}You can zoom in and out and tilt your view by using the mouse wheel. You can also move your view by pushing the mouse to the edge of the screen.
{Prologue_Hastings_Tilt_Camera_RTS_Text_01_Title}Camera Tilt 
{Prologue_Hastings_Unit_Status_Text_01_Text1}While your units are engaging the enemy, move your mouse cursor over your units or the enemy units for feedback on their status. You can find out who is winning and how each unit is faring.
{Prologue_Hastings_Unit_Status_Text_01_Title}Unit Status 
{Prologue_Hastings_Using_Archers_Text_01_Text1}Your fine Norman archers will make short work of these peasants. Use your archers to fire on enemies as they approach, but remember not to engage them in melee.
{Prologue_Hastings_Using_Archers_Text_01_Title}Using Archers 
{Prologue_Hastings_Wait_Here_Text_01_Text1}Your father, Duke William, wishes your troops to guard the rear of his army and wait for his call to battle. Keep a watchful eye for any Saxons that hope to ambush our army!
{Prologue_Hastings_Wait_Here_Text_01_Title}Guard the Rear 
{Prologue_Hastings_Walking_Is_Better_Text_01_Text1}Sometimes it is necessary to run on the battlefield. However, making your troops run too often will tire them out quickly. Order your troops to march long distances and only run when you are near your enemy.
{Prologue_Hastings_Walking_Is_Better_Text_01_Title}Energy to Fight 
{Prologue_Hastings_Zoom_On_Action_Text_01_Text1}You can zoom in on the action by using the mouse wheel. Try zooming in on your infantry now to see your men in the heat of battle.
{Prologue_Hastings_Zoom_On_Action_Text_01_Title}Zoom in on Action 
{Prologue_London_Captured_Text_01_Text1}Well done, my lord! England's great capital is now under Norman control. Double left-click on London to bring up the settlement scroll.
{Prologue_London_Captured_Text_01_Title}London Captured 
{Prologue_London_Deployment_3_Text_01_Text1}You can now deploy your remaining units in the same way. When you are ready to continue, click the 'Start Battle' button.
{Prologue_London_Deployment_3_Text_01_Title}Deployment 
{Prologue_London_Deployment_Text_01_Text1}Before you start the battle, you can position your troops for a more effective attack. First, deploy your Ram in line with the enemy gate to expediate their attack. Select your Ram and right-click on the highlighted position to deploy it.
{Prologue_London_Deployment_Text_01_Title}Deployment 
{Prologue_London_Intro_Text_01_Text1}To conquer England, William must first conquer the English capital, London. To be victorious in a siege battle, you must capture and hold the city's plaza or destroy the enemy army.
{Prologue_London_Intro_Text_01_Title}London 
{Prologue_London_Lost_Text_01_Text1}William's siege against London has failed. You will need to load the save game from the start of the turn or restart the Tutorial. To load the save game, press the 'Esc' key and click Load Game. Select the first save game on the list and click the Load Game button.
{Prologue_London_Lost_Text_01_Title}London Siege Lost! 
{Prologue_London_Sieging_A_City_Text_01_Text1}To reach the enemy plaza, you must first fight through the enemy's troops on the streets. Once you have reached the plaza, kill all the enemy units and the victory timer will commence. Hold the plaza until the timer runs out to gain victory!
{Prologue_London_Sieging_A_City_Text_01_Title}Sieging Cities 
{Prologue_London_Start_Deployment_Intro_Text_01_Text1}When attacking an enemy, you have the option to assess the weather conditions. You can decide to attack immediately or wait to see if the weather will change. Enter the battle now by clicking the 'Start Deployment' button.
{Prologue_London_Start_Deployment_Intro_Text_01_Title}Start Deployment 
{Prologue_London_Take_Plaza_Text_01_Text1}Well done! You have breached the enemy gates. To win the siege, you will need to take and hold the central plaza for three minutes. The plaza is the large stone square in the centre of the city. When there are no enemy units in the plaza, your troops will have control and the victory timer will commence.
{Prologue_London_Take_Plaza_Text_01_Title}Take the Plaza 
{Prologue_London_Using_Ram_Text_01_Text1}Now select your Ram by selecting it on the battlefield or clicking on the unit card with the Ram icon. When your Ram is selected, move your mouse cursor over the enemy gate. When your cursor changes to a wall-breaking icon, right-click on the gate to attack.
{Prologue_London_Using_Ram_Text_01_Title}Using a Ram 
{Prologue_Missions_Scroll_Text_01_Text1}From time to time, you will receive special missions from the Pope, your Council of Nobles, guilds and other factions. You can review the details of your current missions here, including goals, time left and associated rewards and penalties.
{Prologue_Missions_Scroll_Text_01_Title}Missions 
{Prologue_Move_Army_Into_Normandy_Text_01_Text1}Now that your army has disembarked, select Rufus and right-click on Caen to move him into the settlement.
{Prologue_Move_Army_Into_Normandy_Text_01_Title}Fortify Caen 
{Prologue_Move_Out_Of_London_2_Text_01_Text1}When you have selected the units you wish to move out, right-click on Nottingham to lay your siege.
{Prologue_Move_Out_Of_London_2_Text_01_Title}Move Out Of London 
{Prologue_Move_Out_Of_London_Text_01_Text1}The reinforcements that you trained in London are ready. Now is a good time to prepare an army to march on Nottingham. Click on London and select the units you wish to move out by holding down the 'Ctrl' key and left-clicking the units. You will need a decent-sized army to take Nottingham, but will also want to leave a couple of units behind to garrison London.
{Prologue_Move_Out_Of_London_Text_01_Title}Move Out of London 
{Prologue_Moving_Armies_Text_01_Text1}The highlighted area around your army shows where they can move this turn. You can move your army by right-clicking anywhere in this area. Right-click on the highlighted position to move Rufus there.
{Prologue_Moving_Armies_Text_01_Title}Moving Armies 
{Prologue_New_Mission_Text_01_Text1}You have received a mission from the Pope. He has requested that you build a church in this settlement to increase the religion of your people. Close the mission message when you are ready.
{Prologue_New_Mission_Text_01_Title}New Mission 
{Prologue_New_Turn_Text_01_Text1}It is a new turn and season in your campaign. Your treasury has been updated, your armies and characters have rested, and your rivals have made their moves. It is now your turn to make your next moves to carry out your strategy.
{Prologue_New_Turn_Text_01_Title}New Turn 
{Prologue_Nottingham_Catapult_Attack_Text_01_Text1}Use your Norman Catapults to attack the Castle towers. Otherwise, the towers will destroy your siege equipment.
{Prologue_Nottingham_Catapult_Attack_Text_01_Title}Catapults 
{Prologue_Nottingham_Deployment1_Text_01_Text1}Deploy your Ram in front of the enemy gate and attack it when the battle starts. This will prevent your Ram from taking more damage than necessary on its way to the gate.
{Prologue_Nottingham_Deployment1_Text_01_Title}Rams 
{Prologue_Nottingham_Deployment2_Text_01_Text1}Siege towers, for fear of falling over, are unable to move up steep hills. As a result, siege towers cannot dock against walls that are upon a slope. For Nottingham castle, you should deploy your siege tower to the left of your army and attack the wall to the left of the enemy gate.
{Prologue_Nottingham_Deployment2_Text_01_Title}Siege Towers 
{Prologue_Nottingham_Deployment3_Text_01_Text1}Your ladders can be mounted on most castle walls. For Nottingham castle, use your Ladder on the wall to the left of the gate - to the left side of your Siege Tower if you have one. This way, your siege equipment will share the incoming fire from the enemy towers.
{Prologue_Nottingham_Deployment3_Text_01_Title}Ladders 
{Prologue_Nottingham_Deployment_Text_01_Text1}Different types of siege equipment are used for different purposes. You will need to deploy and use them accordingly. Rams break through enemy gates, while ladders and siege towers allow your men to scale enemy walls and gain a foothold upon them.
{Prologue_Nottingham_Deployment_Text_01_Title}Deployment 
{Prologue_Nottingham_Dominate_The_Plaza_Text_01_Text1}You have taken control of the Castle's main plaza. A countdown timer has appeared at the top-right of the screen. Keep the plaza clear of enemies for three minutes and you will win this siege! If your enemies gain a hold on the plaza, the countdown will stop and you will need to remove them and start over.
{Prologue_Nottingham_Dominate_The_Plaza_Text_01_Title}Dominate the Plaza 
{Prologue_Nottingham_Draw_Fire_Text_01_Text1}Before you attack with your siege equipment, send some of your infantry forwards to draw fire from the enemy archers and towers. Otherwise, your valuable siege equipment will take the full force of the castle defences.
{Prologue_Nottingham_Draw_Fire_Text_01_Title}Draw Fire 
{Prologue_Nottingham_Intro_Text_01_Text1}The last great obstacle between Duke William and the English throne is Nottingham Castle. Taking London was a glorious achievement for the Normans, but capturing Nottingham will prove a much sterner challenge.
{Prologue_Nottingham_Intro_Text_01_Title}Nottingham Castle 
{Prologue_Nottingham_Lost_Text_01_Text1}My lord, the Saxons have bested us this time, but we must persist! Return to London and retrain the army for another assault.
{Prologue_Nottingham_Lost_Text_01_Title}Nottingham Siege Lost! 
{Prologue_Nottingham_Storm_Castle_Text_01_Text1}You have broken through the enemy defences! Now you must storm the Castle with your forces and make for the Castle's main plaza. When you reach the plaza, defeat or rout all enemies there to take control of the Castle.
{Prologue_Nottingham_Storm_Castle_Text_01_Title}Storm the Castle 
{Prologue_Open_Caen_Text_01_Text1}As you will have noticed, Caen is a castle. Open its settlement scroll to find out more about castles.
{Prologue_Open_Caen_Text_01_Title}Castles 
{Prologue_Pope_Scroll_Text_01_Text1}As a Catholic nation, your relationship with the Pope and adherence to your religion are highly important. You should bear each faction’s standing with the Pope in mind during your dealings with those factions in future.
{Prologue_Pope_Scroll_Text_01_Title}The Pope 
{Prologue_Pre_Siege_Nottingham_Text_01_Text1}Remember that you need siege equipment to attack a settlement. Nottingham is a castle, which has tougher defences than a city. Click the Ram, Siege Tower and Ladder to add one of each to your construction queue. Then click the 'Maintain siege' button.
{Prologue_Pre_Siege_Nottingham_Text_01_Title}Sieging a Settlement 
{Prologue_Pre_Siege_Window_Text_01_Text1}Before you can siege a settlement, you must build siege equipment. Left-click on the Ram to add it to the queue. Then click the 'Maintain siege' button to begin construction.
{Prologue_Pre_Siege_Window_Text_01_Title}Sieging a Settlement 
{Prologue_Prebattle_Text_01_Text1}This scroll allows you to review the balance of power before you enter a battle. Winning a battle isn't just about troop numbers. The types of units and the generals' command ability are essential. Click the 'Fight battle' button to enter the battle or 'Automatically resolve' to automatically determine the outcome. If you automatically resolve this battle, you will miss the siege tutorial.
{Prologue_Prebattle_Text_01_Title}Prepare for Battle 
{Prologue_Prisoners_Text_01_Text1}You have taken prisoners from your victorious battle and can now decide their fate. Will you be the dread lord and execute them or the chivalrous knight and return their freedom?
{Prologue_Prisoners_Text_01_Title}Prisoners of War 
{Prologue_Ready_To_Siege_Text_01_Text1}Your siege equipment is now completed and you can attack the settlement. Select William and right-click on London. Left-click the 'Assault' button to besiege the settlement.
{Prologue_Ready_To_Siege_Text_01_Title}Ready to Siege 
{Prologue_Rebels_Near_Caen_Text_01_Text1}A rebel army has appeared near Caen. Caen is undefended and you will need to reinforce it quickly or you will lose it.
{Prologue_Rebels_Near_Caen_Text_01_Title}Rebels Near Caen 
{Prologue_Recruit_Units_London_Text_01_Text1}Now open Caen's settlement scroll and recruit some reinforcements there.
{Prologue_Recruit_Units_London_Text_01_Title}Recruit Units in Caen 
{Prologue_Recruitment_Basics_2_Text_01_Text1}Click on the available units to add them to your recruitment queue. The units in the queue highlighted in green will be ready next turn.
{Prologue_Recruitment_Basics_2_Text_01_Title}Recruitment Basics 
{Prologue_Recruitment_Basics_Text_01_Text1}Now is a good time to recruit some reinforcements for your upcoming battles. You are now viewing the construction options. Click the Recruitment tab to view the units that are available to recruit.
{Prologue_Recruitment_Basics_Text_01_Title}Recruitment Basics 
{Prologue_Retrain_Units_Text_01_Text1}You can retrain units that have suffered losses in the same way. Click on the Retrain tab and add your units to the recruitment queue. Your units will be retrained to full complement.
{Prologue_Retrain_Units_Text_01_Title}Retraining Units 
{Prologue_Rufus_Army_Basics_Text_01_Text1}The character cards in the bottom panel of the screen show the units that make up your army. The card on the left belongs to your general. The other cards belong to the units in your army. You can right-click on any card to find out more information about that unit. Right-click on Rufus' character card now for detailed information about him.
{Prologue_Rufus_Army_Basics_Text_01_Title}Generals and Armies 
{Prologue_Rufus_Out_Of_Moves_Text_01_Text1}Rufus is unable to move any further this turn. Press the 'End Turn' button and he can continue his journey next turn.
{Prologue_Rufus_Out_Of_Moves_Text_01_Title}Out of Moves 
{Prologue_Rufus_Scroll_Basics_Text_01_Text1}This scroll shows you the details of your general. You can view the details of any character in the same way. A character's attributes impact on how well they will do their job. Close the scroll when you are ready by left-clicking the close button on the bottom right.
{Prologue_Rufus_Scroll_Basics_Text_01_Title}Character Scroll 
{Prologue_Settlement_Basics_Text_01_Text1}From this scroll, you can construct buildings, recruit troops and manage your settlement.
{Prologue_Settlement_Basics_Text_01_Title}Settlement Basics 
{Prologue_Take_England_Text_01_Text1}Your next goal is to lead William the Conqueror to take England's capital, London. Select William and right-click on London to attack.
{Prologue_Take_England_Text_01_Title}Take England 
{Prologue_This_is_Rufus_Text_01_Text1}Rufus is one of your generals and son of William the Conqueror. If William's campaign to seize the English throne is successful, Rufus will one day be the King of England. Left-click on Rufus now to select him.
{Prologue_This_is_Rufus_Text_01_Title}Meet Rufus 
{Prologue_Welcome_First_Turn_1_Text_01_Text1}Greetings, Sire, I am Lady Gwendolyn. I will guide you on expanding and managing your empire. Your Normans achieved a mighty victory at Hastings! Now you must lead William the Conqueror to claim the English throne. Follow my instructions and we will lead the Normans to glory! To continue, left-click on my portrait.
{Prologue_Welcome_First_Turn_1_Text_01_Title}Norman Conquest 
{Prologue_Welcome_First_Turn_3_Text_01_Text1}You are now viewing England on the campaign map. Here you will build cities, raise armies, and move them to attack your enemies. Parts of the map you have not yet explored are shrouded in darkness. As you move your armies further afield, more of the map will be revealed to you. 
{Prologue_Welcome_First_Turn_3_Text_01_Title}The campaign map 
{Prologue_Welcome_First_Turn_4_Text_01_Text1}You can move your view of the campaign map with the keypad and zoom in and out by using the mouse wheel. Try this now.
{Prologue_Welcome_First_Turn_4_Text_01_Title}Navigating the campaign map 
{Prologue_Welcome_First_Turn_5_Text_01_Text1}You will notice that you cannot move past England. You are restricted to England for now, but once your Norman forces have taken control, you will be ready to wage total war on the rest of Europe and beyond.
{Prologue_Welcome_First_Turn_5_Text_01_Title}Navigating the campaign map 
{Prologue_William_Out_Of_Moves_Text_01_Text1}William is unable to move any further this turn. Press the 'End Turn' button and he can continue his journey next turn.
{Prologue_William_Out_Of_Moves_Text_01_Title}Out of Moves 
{Prologue_You_Win_Text_01_Text1}With King Harold defeated, and London and Nottingham under your control, England is at your mercy! It is now up to you to lead England to glory by expanding your empire to the rest of Europe ... and beyond!
{Prologue_You_Win_Text_01_Title}England is Yours! 
